<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of such things as are happened in the armie of my lordes the princes of Nauarre, and of Condey, since the moneth of September last. 1568 Seene and allowed.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1569</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112655</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847901</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847901</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12965</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01155)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12965)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 241:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of such things as are happened in the armie of my lordes the princes of Nauarre, and of Condey, since the moneth of September last. 1568 Seene and allowed.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Bynneman, for Lucas Haryson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1569.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A discourse of the last Frenche warres.</note>
                  <note>First leaf blank.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12965:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12965:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A diſcourſe of</hi> ſuch things as are <hi>happened in the armie</hi> of my lordes the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>of Nauarre, and of</hi> Condey, ſince the moneth of September laſt. 1568.</p>
            <p>Seene and allowed.</p>
            <p>¶ Jmprinted at London, by Henry Byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neman, for Lucas Haryſon. 1569.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12965:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12965:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe of things <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in Fraunce, ſince the</hi> Moneth of September. <hi>Anno. 1568.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and prouidence, with manifeſt help and fatherly care had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn (as al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know) the Prince of Condyes grace, and my Lord the Admiral from the extreme pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill, and almoſt vnaduoydable daunger of their liues, in whiche they were at <hi>Noyers</hi> and <hi>Tanlag,</hi> he guyded and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted them to <hi>Rochel:</hi> (from one parte of the Realme to the other) without any harme or daunger, with their wyues and children, yea their cradles and nourſes, with ſmall trayne, and greate iourneys, by bye wayes &amp; villages, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome and ill appoynted. Not long after, continuing his goodneſſe and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour towardes Monſieur <hi>Dandelot,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12965:3"/> which was in Britayne, ſo aſſiſted him, that thoughe he were purſued by the Lordes <hi>Montpenſier</hi> and <hi>Martigues,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with great ſtrength both of footemen and horſemen, to hynder his ioyning with the prince, this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, beyonde al expectation he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ouer the riuer of <hi>Loyre,</hi> with all his troupe in their ſight, at a foorde, whiche was neuer marked or knowen of the dwellers them ſelues. The fauour of God appeared alſo in the paſſage of the Queene of <hi>Nauarre</hi> and the Prince hir ſonne, whiche went through the whole countrey of <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi> paſſed the riuer of <hi>Garonne</hi> &amp; <hi>Dordoigne,</hi> with other riuers, foordes and perillous ſtreights though they were ſtraightly followed by the Lordes of <hi>Montluc, Terides, Deſcare,</hi> and <hi>Loſſes</hi> with great force, without any hyndrance at all. The like was ſéene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the paſſage of Monſieur <hi>Dacier</hi> whiche marched with all his troupe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the whole countreys of <hi>Dalphine, Languedoc</hi> and <hi>Gaſcoigne,</hi> to méete with
<pb facs="tcp:12965:3"/> my lordes the Princes, in the ſight and knowledge of the Lorde <hi>Ioyeuſe,</hi> which had expreſſe charge to ſtay hym: ſo that in deſpite of the ſayd Princes enemies, they haue gathered together from all corners of this realme, to the number of fiue and twenty thouſande hargebou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziers, and fiue or ſixe thouſande horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, notwithſtanding the order taken by their ſayd enemies at all portes, brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſtraights and paſſages, and hauing their armie ready foure monethes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, wherwith (God be thanked) they coulde neuer touche the ſayde Lordes princes, or let them from taking of their townes of <hi>S. Maxant, Fontenay, Nyort, Coignac, Xantes, S. Iohn d' Angely, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouleſme, Ponts, Bourg, Taillebourg, Tail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemont,</hi> and other townes, from the riuer of <hi>Gyronde,</hi> vnto the ſuburbes of <hi>Salmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> vpon <hi>Loyre,</hi> ſome by compoſition and other ſome by force. And though the ſame were done in the ſight of all men, but onely that the ſayde Lorde Princes were at the ſiege before the ſayd towne
<pb facs="tcp:12965:4"/> of <hi>Ponts,</hi> they were aduertiſed that the ſayde Lord of <hi>Aſſier</hi> was arriued with his troupe at <hi>Aubeterre,</hi> whiche was with a hundreth and thrée ſcore enſeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of footeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beyng in number a four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene thouſand harguebouziers, and ſixe thouſande pikemen, &amp; twelue hundreth horſemen: and that the enimies had ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>denly taken the Captayne <hi>Mauuance,</hi> and the Captayne <hi>Pieregourdis,</hi> and had ouerthrowen them with certayne num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of their ſouldiers, whiche cauſed the ſayde Princes, fearyng ſome greater miſchief, to marche with their armie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the ſayde place of <hi>Aubeterre,</hi> myndyng to fyght with the enemies yf they woulde ſtande to it: who ſo ſoone as they had newes of the Princes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, remoued incontine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And bicauſe they vnderſtoode they toke the way to <hi>Poitiers,</hi> they determined to ouertake them if it might be with as great iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys as was poſſible, ſéeking al meanes to make them come to the battayle, wherein they vſed ſuche diligence, that
<pb facs="tcp:12965:4"/> the thirde day they were ſo nygh them, that where the fore warde of the ſayde Princes lodged, the enemies were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodged a little before: and oftentimes they found their bread, munition and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, ſo that ſeing them ſelues purſued ſo nygh, they were conſtrained to retire to <hi>Chaſtellerault</hi> and thoſe partes, where they entrenched them ſelues and their artillerie, and mette with Monſieur the kinges brother with new force. And for that it was reported by the Gentlemen that wer ſent to deſcry them neare, that the commyng to them was ſo daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe and harde, that it had bene to no purpoſe, and without reaſon to aſſayle them in their campe, whiche they had ſo well fortified with trenches, and ſo well prouided with munition and artillery, whiche dyd ſo beate the ſayde commers therto, that it had ben vnpoſſible to kepe aray without great loſſe of men: it was determined to preſent them ſelues to the ſight of the army, to ſée if they would come out of their fort, whiche was done
<pb facs="tcp:12965:5"/> by the lord Admiral with his foreward whiche he kept a whole day in battayle raye on the top of a hill, from whence they might ſée the ſayde towne of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellerault,</hi> but the enemies made no cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of comming out to them. For this cauſe deuiſing howe they might get them out of their forte, to a place where the ſayd princes might fight with them, they cauſed their army to marche to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes <hi>Mirebalois,</hi> whiche is a very good and frutefull countrey, and whence their enemies had their moſt commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of vittayles, &amp; where the ſaid princes might beſt vittayle their men to the hinderance of their enemies. And draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thetherward, it hapned that the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies appoynted to lodge at the ſame place where the Princes army was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. And that monſieur the <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Dandelot</hi> his brother approchyng nyghe their lodgyng, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed wyth foure or fiue Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth horſemen at the moſt, they diſcry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their enimies whiche had all their
<pb facs="tcp:12965:5"/> horſemen of the fore warde, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of two thouſande horſe. So that the ſayd Admirall ſent incontinently on all partes for al the troupes of horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as well of the battayle as of the foreward, delaying ſtill tyll the ſayde Princes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to appeare with their battayle and other troupes of the fore warde, which ſomewhat abaſhed the enemies, &amp; then they cauſed certayn harquebouziers to approche nygh the enimies, and there was ſhot on bothe ſides: but bicauſe it was vpon the cloſing in of day, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to waxe very darke, the battayle was deferred tyll the next day, at which tyme the ſayd Princes with al their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies began to marche by breake of day ſtraight to the place where they had left their enemies the euen before, and the ſayde princes perceyuing that they were departed, cauſed certayne cornettes of horſemen to poſt after the ſaid enemies, to deſcry whiche way they toke, and to aſſay once againe if they coulde prouoke them to fight. Whiche they dyd to a vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage
<pb facs="tcp:12965:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> named <hi>Sauſay,</hi> where the lordes of <hi>Guyſe, Martigues, Briſſac, Tauannes, Sanſac,</hi> and diuerſe other had lyen that night, who were not the laſt that toke their héeles, and that with ſuch haſt, that they left all their cariage behinde them, whiche was not leſſe woorth than two hundreth thouſand crownes, and eyght or nyne ſcore drawing horſes, with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne pouder. The ſayd Princes being aduertiſed that all the fore warde of the enemies was out of aray and confuſed, and that <hi>Mountſalan</hi> amongeſt others was put to flight, and the moſt part of his company ſlayne and taken, and had their cornettes and enſeignes, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to marche as faſt as they coulde af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them to ouertake them, whiche they coulde not do till they came to a village named <hi>Iazeneuil,</hi> into whiche the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies retyred, and where the Kings bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had fortified and trenched himſelfe with his artillerye. Where the Princes gaue them the braueſt ſkirmiſhe that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by memory of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which
<pb facs="tcp:12965:6"/> laſted no leſſe than fower or fyue long houres, where was ſhot on bothe ſides, aboue foureſcore thouſand harquebouze ſhot, and three hundreth ſeuen and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie great ſhot on the enemies ſyde only, for that the Princes great ſhot was not brought from the ſiege of <hi>Ponts:</hi> and it was found by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of the enimies themſelues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they loſt at this ſkirmiſhe fiue or ſixe hundreth Souldioures, and fiftene or ſixtene Captaines: and on the Princes ſide there were two hundreth hurt and ſlain. Yet it was written to the Quéene by ſome of hir truſty ſeruaunts that are in the enimies campe, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer French kings ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne was in ſo great danger, as my Lord the kings brother, for the ſpace of thrée dayes and thrée nights: and in déede it is moſte certaine that at the ſame ſkirmiſh, the ſaid Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces footemen wanne the trenches twiſe or thriſe, and ſet vpon the Artillerie, and killed ſome at their péeces, yea that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Souldioures entred into cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine houſes which were within the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies
<pb facs="tcp:12965:7"/> Fort, and brought away armor, and eate and dranke, whereof they had great nede: for that thrée dayes togither they wanted vitailes, yet were they ſo pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and ſo deſirous to fight, that they forgatte the hunger that they ſuffred. This ſkirmiſh being ended, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> means of the night, the ſaide Princes ordained that the next day by breake of day, they ſhould preſent them ſelues in the ſame place of <hi>Iazeuenil,</hi> to ſée if they coulde prouoke the enimie to fight. Which was done, but none of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enimies durſt ſhew their heades, ſauing a hundreth or ſixe ſcore horſemen, and that ſo nighe their fort, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was impoſſible to buckle with them. Since they had newes that they were retired to <hi>Luzignon,</hi> and thence to <hi>Poitiers:</hi> which cauſed the ſaid Princes to lodge their armie in the Countrey of <hi>Myrebalois,</hi> wher they found great qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of bread and munitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies had cauſed to be prouided, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that they wer come to lodge at <hi>Auſance,</hi> which is within a league of
<pb facs="tcp:12965:7"/> 
               <hi>Poitiers,</hi> and foure leagues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the place wher the ſaid Princes lodged, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared them ſuche an enterpriſe, that the ſaide Lord Admirall with a thouſande horſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and only two thouſand harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouziers, droue the ſaid enimies into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd village of <hi>Auſance,</hi> bet them from a bridge which was there, and put all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armie to flight, who retired into <hi>Poitiers</hi> in great diſorder and confuſion with the loſſe of many of their men, &amp; of all their cariage. And although things paſſed in this wiſe, yet are the ſaid enimies ſo ſhameleſſe, that they giue out rumours wholly contrary to the truthe, yea they ſent letters to the Court wherein they were not aſhamed to ſend worde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they withſtoode the ſaid Princes, where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually they put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to flight, &amp; ſought all meanes poſſible to prouoke them to fight. Whereto the ſaid Lords Princes ſéeing their enimies haue ſo little luſt, by reſon of the ill ſucceſſe that they had in the former encounters, to enforce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fight, and (will they nill they) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent
<pb facs="tcp:12965:8"/> ſuch ſubtilties and diſguiſings as they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly vſed, this other day in the ſight of their enimies, and of all theyr campe, they toke a towne and caſtle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to one of the principall heads of their armie, although the ſayd Towne was furniſhed with men, artillerie, &amp; all other kinde of munition, as he to whom it belongeth, hathe had good meane and leiſure to do: the taking whereof ſhalbe ſo cleare and euident witneſſe of it ſelf, of the faint courage that they haue to fight, that they ſhall neuer be able here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to diſguiſe &amp; coloure their cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe as they haue done heretofore. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſaid Lord Princes, ſéeing that neither the taking of the ſayde towne &amp; caſtle, nor anye other occaſion that they could giue to the enimies, could prouoke them to fight, and that they kept them ſelues alwayes on the farther ſide of the riuer of <hi>Clain,</hi> whyther they fled when they were driuen from <hi>Auſance,</hi> hauing further a good riuer before them, &amp; ſonke all the boates to hinder any enterpriſe
<pb facs="tcp:12965:8"/> that might be attempted againſt them: giuing out y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they taried for the ſtrength that came with the Seigneur of <hi>Ioyeuſe</hi> which they ſaide was of ſixe thouſande hargebouziers &amp; fiftene hundreth horſe men: and then they determined to fight with the armie of the ſaid princes. This cauſed the Princes (to giue them newe occaſion to paſſe the riuer, &amp; to encreaſe their will and deſire to fight) to force in their ſight the towne of <hi>Salmure,</hi> which is a paſſage of the Riuer of <hi>Loire,</hi> which draue the enimies into ſuche a ielouſie, that they prepared themſelues to hinder the ſaid Princes from taking of that towne, and for this cauſe they marched forth their armie, lodging their fotemen in one of the Suburbes, but when the batterie was readie, tidings came y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ennimies had paſſed ouer the Riuer of <hi>Clain,</hi> making a countenaunce to come to the reſcuing of <hi>Salmure,</hi> with the forſe of the Lorde of <hi>Ioyeuſe,</hi> which was arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued two or thrée dayes before, which
<pb facs="tcp:12965:9"/> made the ſaide Princes immediately to raiſe their ſiege from <hi>Salmure,</hi> cauſing their armie to marche ſtraight vpon the enimies, which was eaſie to be done, for that there was no riuer betwéene them and the ſaid enimies which they mette before the towne of <hi>Loudun,</hi> which were appointed to lodge in the Suburbes, wher their lodging was ordained, from whence my Lorde the Admirall raiſed them, ſo that they retired and camped in the places &amp; villages about the ſaide <hi>Loudun.</hi> The next day the two armies faced one an other, their ſcoutes being within an hundreth paces the one of the other. They ſhot their Ordinaunce on bothe partes, and ſo paſſed all that day with certain ſmall ſkirmiſhes only. And although the enimies had encamped the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to the vauntage, which common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they do that choſe their place firſt, and might haue approched the ſayd Princes armie without any daunger, which the ſaid Princes could not doe to them, yet
<pb facs="tcp:12965:9"/> when they ſtept two paces, the Princes armie ſtept foure to ioyne with them: two dayes after the ſayde two armies met againe in the ſame places, as they likewiſe did the day after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces could neuer gette them from theyr vauntage, which is maruellous, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the bruites that they gaue abrode, that they were ſo ſtrengthned with the Lord of <hi>Ioyeuſes</hi> power, that they deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined not to depart the places till they had fought with the ſaid Princes army, and ſaid alſo that they had expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement ſo to doe, or at the leaſt to raiſe them from that place, for thereon depended the honor of both the armies. But how ſoone this hot corage was coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, is eaſie to be iudged by their ſodain retiring a league backe from the place which they had taken, &amp; getting a brooke betwéene them, and the ſaid Princes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. Who being not content wyth the vauntage that they wanne of their ſayd enimies, in raiſing them from the place
<pb facs="tcp:12965:10"/> that they ſayd they choſe to fight on, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them to the ſecond place, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe the ſayd enimies had a great vauntage by reaſon of the brooke which made them hard to be come by, yet what with cannon ſhot and continual ſkirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes that they gaue them, they conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them againe to leane that ſeconde place, &amp; to retire, (yea the kings brother himſelf) towards <hi>Chinon,</hi> &amp; to paſſe the riuer of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ienna,</hi> leauing all their ſicke behinde them, and much of their cariage &amp; munitions. The Princes ſéeing this, appointed certaine troupes of horſemen and foote men to follow them which ſet vpon one place of the enimies where there were ſeuen Enſignes, whereof foure were put to flight, and the other thrée wholly diſcomfited, and theyr en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes were burned in a houſe, where ſome of the ſouldiours had withdrawne them ſelues. Afterwarde the ſaid Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſéeyng all meanes of fighting to be taken away, by reaſon of a great and
<pb facs="tcp:12965:10"/> ſtrong riuer betwene them, determined to marche with their army towardes <hi>Towars</hi> and <hi>Montreuilbellay,</hi> as well to refreſhe them and for commoditie of vitayles, whereof they had great néede for fiue or ſixe dayes, as to coaſt the army of the enemies, which being thus retired, diminiſheth and breaketh away dayly by litle and litle, ſo that we heare from diuers places, that they talke of paſſing ouer the riuer of <hi>Loyre</hi> agayne: to place part of their Armie in all the townes that lye on the ſayd riuer, and to border it with warriours at all the brydges, gates, paſſages and villages, and the other part to ſend towardes the campe that the King leuyeth againſt the Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Swebrug.</hi> Which cauſeth the ſayd Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces nowe to determine, that as ſoone as they haue receiued thoſe ten thouſand footemen, and twelue hundreth horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the foure Vicountes of <hi>Bourniquel, Poulin, Monclay</hi> and <hi>Calmont,</hi> bring vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:12965:11"/> them to ſtrenghten them, and which are almoſt arriued at their campe, to marche forewarde to the ſiege of ſome one of thoſe townes on the ſayde riuer, that they may with all expedition ioyne with the prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> &amp; the duke of <hi>Swebrug.</hi> From whom they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued newes by certayne Gentlemen that they haue ſent vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they are not leſſe than fiue and twentie or thirtie thouſande horſemen, and thrée ſcore thouſande footemen when they be al mette. In the meane whyle the ſayde Lord Princes haue <hi>35.</hi> enſeignes of foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and twelue guydons whiche they haue wonne of the enemies, beſides the ſeuen enſeignes of companies of foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that were diſcomfited, at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from before <hi>Loudun,</hi> which wer burnt in the lodgyng to haue the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that were within. On the other ſide, the ſayde foure Vicountes loſt no time where they were, but toke and put to fire and ſworde the towne of <hi>Gaillac</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12965:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> in whiche diuers cruelties with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous ſtoutneſſe had bene committed againſt thoſe of the Religion, and alſo the lowe towne of <hi>Carcaſſonne</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by them, with twelue or fiftene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther townes Monſieur of <hi>Grammont</hi> in the countrey of <hi>Baſque</hi> hath alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fited the ſeigneur of <hi>Luye</hi> which had raiſed foure thouſand me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt thoſe of the Religion, &amp; won certayne péeces of artillerie from him. The Cardinal of <hi>Lorayne</hi> perceyuyng that al things we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not on his ſide as he hoped and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, cauſed the Quene to ſend out Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ. <hi>Portall</hi> the generall receiuer, to make ſome motion of peace, to the ſayd Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to whom the lyke aunſwere was made, that was made to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maiſter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes <hi>Malaſsiſe,</hi> that was alſo ſent by the Quene to the lyke ende, whiche is this, that as long as the Cardinall of <hi>Lorayne</hi> ruled and vſed ſuche tiranny ouer Fraunce, and namely the kinges counſel, out of whiche they haue driuen
<pb facs="tcp:12965:12"/> away my Lorde the Chancelour, and the principall Officers of the crowne, they woulde accept no letters nor meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages made vnder the name of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, but onely as commyng from the forge and inuention of the ſayde Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, and that they had vſed ſo muche vnfaithfulneſſe in the treaty of peaces heretofore, that thoſe of the Religion are driuen to this extremitie, to beleue that there is none other ſafetie for them, but by the meane of the ſworde.</p>
            <p>Since that tyme the companye of Monſieur <hi>Dinoy,</hi> tooke the laſt of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cembre in the ſuburbes of <hi>Chynon</hi> four ſcore <hi>Switſers</hi> with the Prouoſt of the Kings Brothers garde, whiche was on the far ſyde the water, from whence the armye fled in great haſt. This is the happy ſucceſſe that it hath pleaſed God hitherto to giue to the affaires of the ſayd Princes, and the reward and reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence that the enemies haue receyued for their treaſon and vnfaithfulneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:12965:12"/> which is more then ſufficiently verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the contentes of the Popes Bull, whiche they ſewed for in the Month of Iune &amp; Iuly laſt, &amp; diſpatched at <hi>Rome,</hi> the laſt of Auguſt folowing, which ſayd ſute ſhal alwayes euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they neuer intended but to breake the faith and publique ſafetye, both promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſworne, &amp; further to reuoke the Edict: whiche came forth anon after, and in ſubſtance hath relation to the layd Bull. Wherby they reuoke all the Edictes whiche haue béen heretofore made in the fauour of thoſe of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as being made in the aſſemblies of men hyred or brybed therto: thoughe it be well knowen, that it was done in the ſolemneſt aſſemblye that euer was made in this realme, namely the Edict of Ianuarie, where all the Princes and Lordes of the Councell of both Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with the greateſt and moſt nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſonages of all the highe Courts of this Realme were preſent, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:12965:13"/> beinge made at the Requeſt of the Eſtates. And for ſufficient proofe to all thoſe of the Religion, that they neuer ment but to aboliſh &amp; bring to naught y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Religion, they declare in expreſſe wordes by the ſame Edict, that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mynded or inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded any other thing, notwithſtanding any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, Lettres patents, and declarations that haue béen giuen forth or otherwiſe, and notwithſtanding the great aſſurance of words, that his Maieſtie hath giuen, as wel to his ſubiects, as to ſtraunge Princes.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12965:13"/>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, by <hi>Henrie Bynneman, dwelling in Knight</hi> Rider ſtreate, at the ſigne of the Marmayde, for Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas Haryſon.</p>
            <p>1569.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
